Guide to the Ohio River Basin Environmental Council Records, 1948-2013 AIS.2017.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Ohio River Basin Environmental Council Records
1948-2013
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Ohio River Basin Environmental Council
AIS.2017.02
4 Linear Feet
Documentation of the actions, research, and communications of the Ohio River Basin Environmental Council (ORBEC), which brought public attention to air and water quality problems caused by the industrialization of Neville Island in Allegheny County. ORBEC was particularly active in stopping approval of the Kosmos Cement Company's plans to burn of hazardous waste in their cement kiln on Neville Island.
Scope and Content Notes
Records documenting the founding, research, activism, and operation of the Ohio River Basin Environmental Council (ORBEC), which existed primarily to oppose the burning of hazardous waste in a cement kiln operated by the Kosmos Cement Company on Neville Island in Allegheny County. The collection is particularly rich in records documenting ORBEC's actions, including publications, research materials, correspondence, and meeting minutes, as well as the work of other community groups around the United States also opposing hazardous waste burning in cement kilns in the early 1990s. Additionally, there is substantial documentation of other environmental groups with which ORBEC was affiliated, including community-based organizations in Pennsylvania in the early 1990s, as well as national and governmental groups. There is also some documentation of the environmental community organizing around the industrialization of Neville Island that continued after ORBEC's most active period in the early 1990s.
Related Material
Group Against Smog and Pollution (GASP) Records, 1968-2002, AIS.1979.21, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
North Area Environmental Council Records, 1968-2001, AIS.1995.08, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Sierra Club Pennsylvania Chapter Records, 1970-1997, AIS.2000.16, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Jeannette Widom Papers Relating to GASP, 1970-1981, AIS.1994.10, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Previous Citation
Ohio River Basin Environmental Council Records, 1948-2013, AIS.2017.02, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Administrative Records, 1991-1994
Series II. Research Files, 1979-1997
Series III. Projects and Actions, 1948-1993
Series IV. Community Groups Opposing Burning Hazardous Waste in Cement Kilns, 1990-1993
Series V. Related Environmental Groups, 1988-2013
Series VI. Meetings and Conferences, 1990-1993
Series VII. Correspondence, 1990-1993
Series VIII. Financial, 1991-1994
History
The Ohio River Basin Environmental Council (ORBEC), was formed in 1991 to bring awareness to the environmental consequences of industrialization on Neville Island, located in the Ohio River west of the City of Pittsburgh. Concerned citizens living on the northern shore of the Ohio River across from Neville Island, a heavily-industrialized area, organized the group and spent several years researching the effects of emissions from the Neville Island factories. They mobilized in the early 1990s to end the approval process that would allow Kosmos Cement to burn hazardous waste as fuel in the cement kiln on Neville Island, in cooperation with the Southdown Corporation which had recently expanded into hazardous waste processing. The burning of hazardous waste was ultimately not approved for the site and members of the group continued to work on other environmental causes. ORBEC remains active, though the bulk of the records in this are from the early 1990s, when the group was actively opposing burning of hazardous waste. The Kosmos Cement kiln on Neville Island was ultimately closed in April 2001.
Cement industries -- United States; Hazardous wastes -- Incineration; Environmental policy -- Pennsylvania -- Citizen participation; Citizens' associations -- United States; Pollution -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Refuse and refuse disposal -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Neville Island (Pa.); Neville Township (Pa.); Southdown, Inc.; Ohio River Basin Environmental Council
- Administrative Records, 1991-1994; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series contains bylaws and typed meeting minutes from ORBEC meetings in the early 1990s, as well as other administrative records, such as blank letterhead and administrative forms, calendars of ORBEC activities, and address lists. There are also several spiral-bound notebooks containing notes on meetings and other events from Janet Strahosky, an early member and record keeper of the group.
  - Bylaws, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Meeting minutes, typewritten, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letterhead, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Blank forms, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Address lists and updates, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sign-in sheets and contact information, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Meeting and event calendars, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Notebooks (meeting notes, to do lists, etc.), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Notebooks (meeting notes, to do lists, etc.), 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Research Files, 1979-1997; II.
  This series contains published research, white papers, news clippings, and other public documents compiled by ORBEC on environmental issues, mainly related to the burning of hazardous waste in the cement industry. Also included is a large file of news clippings from local and national sources on subjects related to ORBEC's work, including pollutants, toxins, and environmental regulations.
  - Toxics, 1989-1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Particulates, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Neville Township, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Waste Technology Industries, 1983-1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - News clippings, 1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Cement Kiln Incineration of Hazardous Waste, A Critique," Dr. Edward W. Kleppinger and Richard A. Carnes, September 1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Safety of Cement Manufactured with Fuel Containing Hazardous Waste," Dr. James Cobb, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - List of kilns burning or proposing to burn hazardous waste, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Projects and Actions, 1948-1993; III.
  Series contains records from ORBEC's projects, largely relating to the Kosmos Cement Company's plan to burn hazardous waste in its cement kilns. Most folders contain research, correspondence, public records obtained by ORBEC, and publications about to Kosmos Cement sites, including industry publications. Research, correspondence, and white papers regarding local, state, and federal regulations are also represented. ORBEC's public comments, signed petitions and letters sent to government officials, and action alerts other documents meant for public use and consumption are also included here. ORBEC was instrumental in starting Environmental Advisory Councils (EACs), which are advisory boards connected to municipal governments, in several Pittsburgh-area locations, including Neville Township, Stowe Township, McKees Rocks, Ben Avon Heights, Bellevue and Avalon. Correspondence, ordinances creating the councils, collected research, and meeting minutes from the EACs are represented here, though records from the Avalon EAC predominate. Also notable are several folders of ORBEC's publications, including newsletters, reports, and press releases.
  - Calgon Corporation, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Kosmos Cement research: published sources, 1983-1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Kosmos Cement kiln research: white papers and unpublished materials, 1982-1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Kosmos Cement kiln research: news clippings, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Kosmos Cement research compiled by Ed Kleppinger, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Kosmos Cement Correspondence, Incoming, 1985-1991 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ohio River Park, 1948-1992 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Riverfront development, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Shenango Group, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Public comments, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Petitions and letters, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Public letters and action alerts, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Reports and press releases, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Ideas for op-eds and newsletter articles, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Newsletters and action alerts, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - News coverage of members and projects, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Environmental Advisory Committees, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Community Groups Opposing Burning Hazardous Waste in Cement Kilns, 1990-1993; IV.
  In the early 1990s, ORBEC was in contact with other community groups and individuals across the United States who opposed the burning of hazardous waste in cement kilns, many of which were operated by Southdown. This series contains correspondence, research, news clippings, letters, public records, and other documents shared with ORBEC by these groups and individuals.
  - Ban The Burn, Fort Collins, CO, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Citizens Aware and United for a Safe Environment, Midlothian, TX, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Concerned Citizens Coalition, Louisville, KY, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Desert Citizens Against Pollution, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Greene Environmental Coalition, Fairborn, OH, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Greene Environmental Coalition, Fairborn, OH, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Mary Money, Hagerstown, MD, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Sally Sevier, Brooksville, FL, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, September 1991 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Related Environmental Groups, 1988-2013; V.
  Series contains information and records about environmental and governmental groups related to ORBEC, including newsletters, correspondence, publications and other documentation. It is divided into two sub-series; the first documents environmental groups based in Pennsylvania, with which ORBEC often had direct working relationships, and the second documents national and governmental groups.
  - Pennsylvania-Based Environmental Groups, 1989-2013; 1.
    Series contains newsletters, correspondence, and publications from Pennsylvania-based environmental groups, many of which are community-based and with whom ORBEC worked closely. Of particular note is the folder on the Kosmos Cement Company Citizens Liaison Committee, which contained several ORBEC members. ORBEC also worked closely with the following organizations represented here: Clean Water Action, North Area Environmental Council, Pennsylvania Environmental Council, GASP, and Pennsylvania Environmental Network. The substantial records from the Chemical Community Advisory Panels are records of meetings between community members and chemical company representatives which, though they occurred after ORBEC was no longer an active organization, represent the continuing work of former ORBEC members.
    - Aristech Chemical Community Advisory Panel, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Aristech/Ashland/Neville Chemical Community Advisory Panel, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Aristech/Ashland Chemical Community Advisory Panel, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Ashland/Neville/Sunoco Chemical Community Advisory Panel, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Ashland/Neville/Sunoco Chemical Community Advisory Panel, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Ashland/Neville/Sunoco Chemical Community Advisory Panel, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Ashland/Neville/Sunoco Chemical Community Advisory Panel, 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Neville Island Community Advisory Panel, 2009-2010 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Neville Island Community Advisory Panel, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Center for Hazardous Materials Research, University of Pittsburgh, 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Clean Water Action/War on Waste, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Clean Water Action, 2000-2009 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Citizen Action of Pennsylvania/Toxic Action, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Citizens Opposed to Unsafe Power, 1991-1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Compost Patch, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - E Watch, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Earth Day Coalition/Air Quality Meeting, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Group Against Smog Pollution (GASP), 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Green Corps, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Kosmos Cement Company Citizens Liaison Committee, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - North Area Environmental Council, 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - PA Cleanways, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Pennsylvania Environmental Council, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Pennsylvania Environmental Network, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Pennsylvania Environmental Network Newsletter, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Protect Environment and Children Everywhere, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Southwestern Pennsylvania Alliance for a Clean Environment/Pittsburgh Against Toxic Incineration, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - National and Governmental Groups, 1988-1994; 2.
    Series contains newsletters, correspondence, and publications from national or non-Pennsylvania-based environmental groups, as well as governmental entities that affected the work of ORBEC. Of particular note is the large amount of material from Greenpeace, the Clean Air Network and the Clean Steel Network, as well as the newsletters of the Environmental Research Foundation.
    - American Chemical Society, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Citizens Clearinghouse for Hazardous Wastes, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Clean Air Network, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Clean Steel Network, National Resources Defense Council, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Environmental Protection Agency, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Environmental Research Foundation/Rachel's Hazardous Waste News, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Great Lakes Protection Fund, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Greenpeace, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Greenpeace, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Local. State, and Federal Emergency Management Agencies, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Sierra Club, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Tennessee Valley Energy Coalition, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Meetings and Conferences, 1990-1993; VI.
  Series contains handouts, agendas, schedules, transcripts and/or hand-written notes from several meetings and conferences on environmental topics. Of note are the undated typewritten transcript of the Allegheny County Local Emergency Managers meeting and the handwritten transcript of what is likely the state Air Pollution Control Board, both from the early 1990s. There are also materials from several conferences, including two years of the Beyond the Right To Know Conference, funded by the United States Public Interest Research Group Education Fund.
  - Allegheny County Local Emergency Planning Committee meeting transcript, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Air Pollution Control Board meeting transcript, December 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Beyond the Right-To-Know Conference, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Beyond the Right-To-Know Conference, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Hazardous Waste Burning in Cement Kilns Press Conference, Allegheny County Commissioner Larry Dunn, February 21, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Pennsylvania Environmental Network Leadership Development Conference, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Pennsylvania Environmental Network Leadership Development Conference, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1990-1993; VII.
  Series contains correspondence with governmental bodies and representatives, as well as some of ORBEC's other outgoing correspondence. Of particular note is the large volume of correspondence with the Allegheny County Commissioners, Allegheny County Health Department, and West View Borough Water Department, as well as the personal correspondence between ORBEC member Janet Strahosky and State Representative David Mayernik.
  - Allegheny County Commissioners, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Allegheny County Health Department, 1990-1993 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Arlen Specter, United States Senate, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Dan Cohen, Pittsburgh City Council, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - David Mayernik, Pennsylvania State House of Representatives, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Fred A. Trello, Pennsylvania State House of Representatives, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - George Wible, Chairman of Ohio Township Board of Supervisors, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Harris Wofford, United States Senate, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Melissa A. Hart, Senate of Pennsylvania, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Resources, Air and Waste Management, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Rick Santorum, United States House of Representatives, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Ronald R. Cowell, Pennsylvania State House of Representatives, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - West View Borough Water Department, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1990-1993 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Financial, 1991-1994; VIII.
  Series contains ORBEC's bank account statements, receipts, and financial statements.
  - Account statements, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Financial statements, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Receipts, 1991-1994 (Box 3, Folder 27)